Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf officially מ"ג. mem gimmel.
We're in מ"ב עמוד ב'. mem bais amud bais. We pick up
about five lines from the top, two dots: אחד בתולות ואחד בעולות.
echad betulot ve'echad be'ulot. Talking about the three months' wait before a
woman gets remarried to determine
whether she's pregnant,
and the משנה mishnah says whether she is a בתולה betulah or
a בעולה, be'ulah, whether it was her first marriage or was אירוסין
erusin or נישואין, nissuin, even though in those cases logically we know
that she's not pregnant. Nevertheless, it's a type of לא פלוג, lo
pelug, but then we hear that Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Yossi both
disagree and say that if the first marriage was only an אירוסין
erusin or if the second one is, then there's no need to
wait, or if it was a נישואין nissuin but right now she's
only undergoing אירוסין, erusin, there's also no need to wait. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says, "היינו בתולות
והיינו ארוסות?" hainu betulot vehainu arusot? Why did it say two things,
virgins and only having been ארוסה? arusa? It's the same thing. "היינו
בעולות והיינו נשואות?" hainu be'ulot vehainu nesuot? Seeing a non-virgin is the
same as being a נשואה. nesua. We should, so why is it
distinguishing them? The גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר: amar
Rav Yehuda hachi ka'amar: this is what it means. אחד בתולות ואחד
בעולות, echad betulot ve'echad be'ulot, whether they are virgins or not, שנתאלמנו
או שנתגרשו בין מן האירוסין בין מן הנישואין. shenisalmenu o shenitgarshu bein
min ha'erusin bein min hanissuin. How do you get those two cases?
Women who were either divorced or widowed from אירוסין erusin and נישואין.
nissuin. Meaning, so אירוסין erusin and נישואין, nissuin, it's just an explanation
of the first two categories, it's not really a different case. All
right. רבי אליעזר לא אתא בי מדרשא. Rabbi Eliezer lo ata bei
midrashah. Rabbi Eliezer didn't come to the בית מדרש. beis medrash. אשכחיה
לרבי אסי. ashkechei le'Rabbi Assi. He found Rabbi Assi. אמר ליה מאי
אמרו רבנן בבי מדרשא? amar lei mai amru rabbanan bevei midrashah?
What did the rabbis say in the בית מדרש? beis medrash? So
Rabbi Assi said, if you want to know, you should have been
there. No. אמר ליה הכי אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוסי. amar
lei hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke'Rabbi Yossi. He said to him,
this is what Rabbi Yochanan said, the הלכה halacha
is like Rabbi Yossi, who says that we don't say לא פלוג.
lo pelug.
Both Rabbi Yossi and Rabbi Yehuda said that it would only be
a problem if the women were originally in נישואין nissuin and they
were now doing a נישואין, nissuin, so there was a possibility of
sex before and sex now, but if it was an אירוסין erusin
at either end, it would not be a problem. Rabbi Yossi made
another point about her being an אבילה, aveilah, which we'll get to.
But anyway, we rule like Rabbi Yossi. So the גמרא Gemara says,
now remember Rabbi Yochanan normally goes like a סתם משנה. stam mishnah.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מכלל דיחידאה פליג עליה? michlal deyichida'ah palig
aleih? Does that suggest that the סתם stam who argues on Rabbi
Yossi and says לא פלוג lo pelug and you always need a
three-month wait, that that סתם stam is really a דעת יחיד, da'as
yachid, is not a consensus or not a majority but only a
single opinion? אין, in, yes, that's it, דתניא, detanya, and I'll show
it to you. We see in a ברייתא. braisa. הרי שהיתה רדופה.
harei shehayisa redufa. So now we're going to have a whole series
of cases where we can assume that the woman is not pregnant,
and we're going to still say that you need a three-month wait.
Okay, the type of the לא פלוג lo pelug of our משנה.
mishnah. הרי שהיתה רדופה לבית אביה. harei shehayisa redufa levei aviha.
This woman was always running out to be in her father's house.
Meaning that during the period leading up to her husband's death, she
had been in her father's house—it's a funny phrase, רדופה—but redufa anyway,
she had not been with her husband for a long period of
time. או שהיה לה כעס בבית בעלה, o shehaya lah ka'as bevei
ba'alah, or she and her husband were having a fight and somehow
we could have an assumption that they weren't having sex during that
time. Again, some of these are very funny because, you know, it's
one thing to say thank you, אירוסין erusin or whatever, something very
formal and sort of measurable. These types of things leave it to
be very vague in terms of determining who falls into that category.
I mean, would it just all be just an issue of self-reporting?
Maybe it would. Anyway,
או שהיה בעלה חבוש בבית האסורין, o shehaya ba'alah chavush bevei ha'asurin,
or the husband was in jail. או שהיה בעלה זקן, o shehaya
ba'alah zaken, or he was elderly, so much so that he could
not, even if they had sex, we could assume that he was
not able to have
children through—we'll get to that. או חולה, o choleh, or he was
sick, so couldn't be having sex. או שהיתה היא חולה, o shehayisa
hi chola, or she was sick. או שהפילה אחר מיתת בעלה, o
shehipila achar misas ba'alah, or she had a miscarriage after her husband's
death, so obviously she's not pregnant. או שהיתה עקרה, o shehayisa akara,
or she was infertile. או זקנה, o zekeina, or elderly, postmenopausal. או
קטנה, o ketana, or too young. או אילונית, o aylonis, or she
was a woman who was born never able to have children. או
שאינה ראויה לילד, o she'eina re'uya laled, or any reason she couldn't
have kids. In all these cases, it doesn't matter, צריכה להמתין ג'
חדשים, דברי רבי מאיר. tzricha lehamtin gimel chodashim, divrei Rabbi Meir. She
has to wait three months. That's what Rabbi Meir says. So anyways,
the point of all that is there is an idea of לא
פלוג lo pelug out there, but it's a דעת יחיד, da'as yachid,
it's Rabbi Meir.
רבי יהודה
מתיר לארס ולהינשא מיד. Rabbi Yehuda matir le'ares ulinasei miyad. And Rabbi
Yehuda, or some have the גירסא girsa of Rabbi Yossi, because both
of them make distinctions between when it can be determined or not
determined. They allow her to do אירוסין erusin right away, meaning even
if she had any—well, if
it was funny, it says לארס ולהינשא מיד, le'ares ulinasei miyad, right,
so even if a woman was נשואה, nesua, she could have אירוסין
erusin right away, and in these cases she could even do נישואין
nissuin right away. Okay, so you see that it is a מחלוקת
machlokes of דעת יחיד, da'as yachid, and therefore Rabbi Yochanan was able
to פסקן pasken like Rabbi Yehuda slash Rabbi Yossi, that it makes
it that it's not a problem for her to marry immediately for
even נישואין nissuin if it was a situation in which she could
not be pregnant.
So the גמרא Gemara says... אמר רבי חייא בר אבא, Amar Rabi
Chiya bar Abba, חזרו בו chazru bo רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan reversed himself and now he's going back to say
לא פלוג lo plug that you always need three months' wait. So,
חזרו בו chazru bo רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, אי הדר ביה, ihadar beh, if he reversed himself, we
must need that ihadar beh. He reversed himself because of the ברייתא
braisa that of the vineyard, meaning of what's mentioned in כרם ביבנה.
Kerem b'Yavneh. דתניא, Detanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי
ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה, Amar Rabi Yishmael b'no shel
Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka, שמעתי מפי חכמים בכרם ביבנה, shamati mipi chachamim
b'Kerem b'Yavneh, I heard from the sages in the כרם ביבנה, Kerem
b'Yavneh, right where the sages gathered after the חורבן בית המקדש, churban
Beis Hamikdash, where the seat of rabbinic sort of authority was in
יבנה, Yavneh, which was called a vineyard because they were like in
rows of sages, כולן צריכות להמתין שלשה חדשים. kulan tzerichos lehamtin shlosha
chadashim. Everybody, all the women, no matter what the circumstances, all need
the three months' wait. We don't make a distinction whether they could
have been whether they could be pregnant whether, you know, whether there
was an opportunity for them to have sex or not to have
sex. אמר ליה רבי ירמיה לרבי זריקה, Amar lei Rabi Yirmiya l'Rabi
Zerika, now we're not done with the discussion. רבי ירמיה Rabi Yirmiya
said to רבי זריקה, Rabi Zerika, כי אילתא לקמיה דרבי אבהו, ki
ayalta l'kamei d'Rabi Abbahu, when you go in front of רבי אבהו,
Rabi Abbahu, רמי ליה, rami lei, show him the following contradiction. מי
אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוסי? mi amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha k'Rabi
Yosi? Does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan rule like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi,
meaning the earlier version of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi that we read,
that we went like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi to say that it
makes a difference whether she could be whether she could have been
having sex or not? ואמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה? v'amar Rabbi
Yochanan halacha k'stam mishna? Doesn't רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say we rule
like a סתם משנה? stam mishna? ותנן, U'tnan, and our משנה mishna
says, כל הנשים לא ינשאו ולא יתארסו עד שיהיו להם שלשה חדשים.
kol hanashim lo yinaseu v'lo yisarsu ad sheyihyu lahem shlosha chadashim. All
women have to wait three months. אחת בתולות ואחת בעולות, Achas besulos
v'achas beulos, whether they have had sex or not have had sex.
Anyway, so you see, so his question is, although before we already
made the point of saying that it was a דעת יחיד, das
yachid, okay, that's just a normal idea that why are you פוסק
pasken like a דעת יחיד das yachid against a רבים? rabbim? So
we're saying, okay, that סתם stam voice in the beginning of the
משנה, mishna, although it was a סתם stam voice was really a
דעת יחיד, das yachid, fine. But even if behind the scenes it's
a דעת יחיד, das yachid, in the משנה mishna it's presented as
a סתם. stam. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that we go
like a סתם. stam. So how could here he be going not
like the סתם? stam? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him,
דמי רמי לך הא, de'rami lach ha, the one who showed you
that who like who showed you that contradiction or who, you know,
asked that question, לא חש לקימחיה, lo chash l'kimchei, is not concerned
for his flour, you know, because learning תורה Torah is often compared
to like grinding wheat and making flour, basically he's not concerned for
the types of questions he asks. That's a lousy question. סתם ואחר
כך מחלוקת, Stam v'achar kach machlokes, that is not a simple סתם
משנה. stam mishna. That is a סתם משנה stam mishna followed by
a debate, because you have the סתם stam voice and then it
says that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagrees. So when רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says we rule like a סתם משנה, stam mishna, it's when
the סתם stam is said in an uncontested way and maybe different
opinions will be found in other משניות mishnayos or in a ברייתא,
braisa, but in that very משנה mishna the opposing voice is voiced
right away. So that's not the context. Now you're still right, you
have to ask the question about יחיד ורבים. yachid rabbim. So we
identified so we identified that that סתם stam behind the scenes really
is a דעת יחיד, das yachid, but in terms of the principle
that you go by a סתם stam regardless of the יחיד ורבים
yachid rabbim question, that's a רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan principle. That's not
true when embedded in that סתם stam is the opposing voice. סתם
ואחר כך מחלוקת, Stam v'achar kach machlokes, ואין הלכה כסתם, v'ein halacha
k'stam,
we don't rule like the סתם, stam, we don't necessarily rule like
the סתם. stam. דאמר רב פפא ואיתימא רבי יוחנן, D'amar Rav Papa
v'isima Rabbi Yochanan, because רב פפא Rav Papa says and some say
even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself says, מחלוקת ואחר כך סתם, machlokes
v'achar kach stam, הלכה כסתם. halacha k'stam.
If you have a debate followed by a סתם משנה, stam mishna,
then we go like the סתם משנה. stam mishna. סתם ואחר כך
מחלוקת, Stam v'achar kach machlokes,
if you have a סתם stam and then the debate follows it,
אין הלכה כסתם, ein halacha k'stam, we don't go like the סתם.
stam. Again, not necessarily meaning we דווקא davka go against the סתם,
stam, but certainly means we're not obligated to go like the סתם
stam in that case. Okay, now we're going to analyze this a
little bit and digress from our discussion to talk about this issue
about do we always say הלכה כסתם halacha k'stam and how do
you understand סתם ואחר כך מחלוקת. stam v'achar kach machlokes. You should
know these types of questions by the way come up all the
time in הלכה halacha and like the you know, there's developed a
whole hermeneutics around interpreting the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. Like if the
שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch has an opinion and then he says ויש
אומרים v'yeish omrim like da-da-da-da-da ויש אומרים דא. v'yeish omrim da. So
okay, which is the הלכה? halacha? The first one or the ויש
אומרים? v'yeish omrim? Let's say he says ויש אומרים v'yeish omrim this
and then he gives you the opinion. So it's sort of like
a similar question, like סתם ויש אומרים, stam v'yeish omrim, ויש אומרים
וסתם, yeish omrim v'stam, there's a whole hermeneutics around the שולחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch about how to interpret that.
סתם משנה רבי מאיר Stam mishna Rabi Meir in general, right?
Yeah, but and here was רבי מאיר Rabi Meir as well. So
that's interesting. You're right that the fact that the גמרא, Gemara, you
know, סתם משנה אליבא דרבי מאיר stam mishna aliba d'Rabi Meir or
is it like, you know, or does it mean that it's like
really just the opinion of רבי מאיר Rabi Meir as opposed to
equal opinions by other, you know, by other it's a good point
that the גמרא Gemara before said, oh, it's not a רבים, rabbim,
it's a רבי מאיר. Rabi Meir. That's what every סתם stam generally
is. All right, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, it's
a סתם ואחר כך מחלוקת. stam v'achar kach machlokes. So we don't
have to rule like this סתם. stam. Although we might in the
end rule like it because of this other משנה mishna about ברייתא
braisa about כרם ביבנה. Kerem b'Yavneh. Now we're going to have a
discussion about this. מסתמיך ואזיל רבי אבהו אכתפיה דרבי נחום. Mistameich v'azil
Rabi Abbahu a'katfeih d'Rabi Nachum. So רבי אבהו Rabi Abbahu was
being supported and being sort of carried on
the shoulders of רבי נחום, Rabi Nachum, שמעיה, shamaeih,
his attendant.
אזיל רבי... Azil Rabi... and the attendant was sort of gathering up
הלכות halachas from רבי אבהו, Rebbi Abavu, you know, figure like if
you're already driving the Rabbi to the airport, you might as well
שמועס shmooze with him and you learn some תורה Torah from him.
So, he was gathering הלכות halachas from him. בעאי מיניה, ba'ei minei,
he asked him: מחלוקת ואחר סתם machlokes v'achar stam מאי? mai? What
do we say in a case where it's a מחלוקת machlokes and
then a סתם? stam? אמר ליה, amalei, he said to him: הלכה
כסתם. halacha k'stam. So then we rule like the סתם. stam. Okay.
סתם ואחר מחלוקת stam v'achar machlokes מאי? mai? If the סתם stam
followed by a מחלוקת, machlokes, what do you say? אמר ליה, amalei,
אין הלכה כסתם. ein halacha k'stam. We don't rule like the סתם.
stam. Again, I'm not sure if he means we don't rule or
we don't necessarily rule. Anyway,
סתם במתניתין מחלוקת בברייתא. stam b'masnisin machlokes b'braisa. Let's say you have
a סתם משנה, stam mishnah, but in a ברייתא braisa it's recorded
as a debate. What do you say? מאי? mai? אמר ליה, amalei,
הלכה כסתם. halacha k'stam. We still go by the סתם, stam, you
know, I mean, if it's almost like a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer,
I mean, you know, even if the debate is in a משנה
mishnah that comes later, we go by the סתם. stam. So certainly
if the debate is, you know, located elsewhere and in the ברייתא,
braisa, we'll go like the סתם משנה. stam mishnah. Okay. What about
this: מחלוקת במתניתין וסתם בברייתא? machlokes b'masnisin v'stam b'braisa? There's a מחלוקת
machlokes in the משנה mishnah and a סתם stam in the ברייתא.
braisa. Now maybe that's better than מחלוקת ואחר סתם machlokes v'achar stam
because at least in the context of the ברייתא, braisa, it's uncontested.
So maybe since in that source it's uncontested, maybe we should go
like it. מאי? mai? אמר ליה, amalei, he said to him: וכי
רבי לא שנאה רבי חייא מנא ליה? v'chi Rebbi lo shna'ah Rebbi
Chiya minalo? If רבי Rebbi didn't teach it, didn't teach this
סתם, stam, meaning that he didn't necessarily buy into the fact that
this was the הלכה, halacha, where does רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya get
the idea that this is necessarily the הלכה? halacha? So what,
I'm sorry what?
מנא ליה? minalei? We find such a case?
No, he would say that why, why do we rely on the
authority of רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya over, you know, basically he's saying
the משנה mishnah has ultimate authority. So just because רבי חייא Rebbi
Chiya has decided to teach it as a סתם, stam, does not
mean that, you know, why should that have authority if רבי Rebbi
apparently chose not to teach it as a סתם stam or not,
you know, not to voice that opinion. Okay. So anyway, which all
that seems pretty obvious because again, you know, if even within the
משנה, mishnah, the only time you go by a סתם stam is
when it's first the סתם stam and then the מחלוקת, machlokes, it
would seem any other configuration of locating where the סתם stam is,
you know, whether you put it, you know, in a ברייתא, braisa,
whether you put it in so on, you know, obviously gives it
lesser weight.
Okay, so that
תוספות Tosafos and
רש״י Rashi give discussion exactly where is the מחלוקת machlokes located in
different מסכתות masechtos in the same משנה, mishnah, later in the same
מסכתא, masechta, later in the same סדר. seder. I'm not going to
get into that. Okay. אמר ליה והתנן. amalei v'ha tnan. Okay, so
now getting back to this issue that we always go like a
סתם, stam, he's going to say one minute, I have a סתם
stam that I know we don't פסקן pasken like. Okay, and this
is the whole thing with these like כללים klalim is that you
never really always go by these כללים. klalim. They're just like general
rules. You know, even... yeah, exactly. That's what I just said. It's
not absolute. Anyway, so it says like this,
right. והתנן, v'ha tnan, we taught in the משנה. mishnah. אמר ליה
והתנן, amalei v'ha tnan, I'll show you a משנה mishnah that we
don't go like a סתם משנה. stam mishnah. We taught:
מסרק של פשתן, masreik shel pishtan, you have a comb used for
combing flax, שניטלו שיניו, shenitlu shinav, that the teeth of the comb
have been removed,
ונשתיירו בו שתים, v'nishtayru bo shtayim, and two of the teeth are
still present. So you know you can use, do something if the
two teeth are next to one another. So in that case, טמאות.
tmeios.
It is... שניטלו שיניו ונשתיירו בו שתים טמאות ואחת טהורה. shenitlu shinav
v'nishtayru bo shtayim tmeios v'achas tehorah. If it's two, then they're טמאות.
tmeios. If it is one, then it is טהורה tehorah because what
are you going to use a comb for that has one tooth
in it? Okay, so it's no longer a vessel receptive to, able
to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. וכולן שניטלו אחת אחת בפני עצמן,
v'chulan shenitlu achas v'achas bifnei atzman, however as far as the comb
is concerned, as far as the individual teeth that break off individually,
טמאות, tmeios, those are טמאות tmeios because you know you could use
a tooth of a comb as like a toothpick or something like
that. Okay. Now של צמר, shel tzemer, if however it's not a
flax comb but a wool comb, שניטלו שיניו, shenitlu shinav, that again
its teeth were removed, אחת בין שתים טהורה. achas bein shtayim tehorah.
If it's one between every two, so there's a gap between the
teeth, then it's טהורה. tehorah. Okay, you got the idea? No two
teeth are next to one another. נשתיירו בו
גמל במקום אחד,
nishtayru bo gimmel
bimkom echad, if there are three in one place, טמא, tamei, then
it's טמא. tamei. Now obviously that's funny because if it said before
if there's a gap it's טהורה, tehorah, you'd suggest that even two
together are טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara will get to that.
הא החיצונה אחת מהן, ha hachitzonah achas mehen, if the outer teeth
is one of these, three in one place, then טהורה, tehorah, then
it is טהורה tehorah because these outer teeth are not as functional
as the inner teeth or whatever רש״י Rashi has different explanations, we
don't have to worry about it. ניטלו דדיהן ועשאן למלקט, nitlu dadeihen
v'ason l'malket, if the two, two teeth were removed and you, they
were sort of combined by the bottom piece of the comb, right,
and they broke off and they're sort of held together, then you
could use it as
a type of a tweezers. So in that case, טמאות, tmeios, the
teeth themselves are טמאות. tmeios. אחת והתקינה לנר או למיתוח, achas v'hitkinah
l'ner o l'mituach, if you have one and you fixed it and
you like, you know, like I don't know whittled it or something
to use it to like clean
as like a lamp cleaner or to like stretch out... Ah, that's
a סתם משנה, stam mishna, and we know that
we don't rule like that. Of all the things to know we
don't rule like, how relevant is that משנה? mishna? Anyway, that was
his question. How can you say we go like a סתם משנה?
stam mishna? Here's a סתם משנה stam mishna we don't go like.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, בר מיניה דהיא, bar
minei d'hi, put that case aside. רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש שמעתיהו ביה,
Rabbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish shamatayhu bei, both say זו אינה משנה. zu
einah mishna. We don't rule like that משנה. mishna. Okay. They say
what? That's an exception. We know we don't rule that way. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? But now the גמרא Gemara is not done. Why
not? Let's give a reason. Why is it an exception?
אמר רב הונא בר מניומי משמיה דרב
אידי בר ריש דרב איקא משום דקשיא רישא לסיפא,
Amar Rav Huna bar Minyumi mishmei d'Rav Idi bar Reish d'Rav Ika
mishum
d'kashya reisha l'seifa, because the משנה mishna itself is internally problematic. The
רישא reisha doesn't, the beginning doesn't agree with the end. דתני, Detani,
the beginning says the wool one שניטלו שיניו אחת מבינו טהור, she'nitlu
shinav achas mi-beino tahor, if there's a gap between the teeth, it's
טהור. tahor. הנשארו בו שתים במקום אחד טמא, Ha-nish'aru bo shtayim b'makom
echad tamei, if two are right next to each other, no gap,
then
טמא. tamei. It's טמא. tamei. והדר תני, V'hadar tani, and then the
end of the end says נשארו בו שלש טמא, nish'aru bo shalosh
tamei, three together are טמא. tamei. שלש
אין שתים לא, Shalosh in, shtayim lo, only three, not two. So
the whole משנה mishna is a problematic
משנה. mishna. ומאי קשיא, U-mai kushya, why is it difficult? דילמא הא
בגבייתא הא בברייתא, Dilma ha b'gavyaysa ha b'varaysa, maybe it's a difference
between the outer teeth and the inner teeth. Because the way רש"י
Rashi basically says is like the outer teeth are for really doing
the, it's like, you know, it's a two-leveled comb. So the outer
teeth are for doing the actual, like, you know, the outer teeth
are higher and the inner teeth are lower and the outer teeth
are actually for like scraping the stuff and removing it and then
the inner teeth are for like collecting the loose stuff that's freed
up. Some something like that. So anyway, it makes a difference whether
the outer teeth or the inner teeth. The outer ones you need
there to be three in one place to be effective, the inner
ones even two in one place. אלא מהכא, Eila mei-hacha, from here.
דתני וכולן שניטלו אחת אחת בפני עצמן טמאות. D'tani v'chulan she'nitlu achas
achas bifnei atzman teme'os. By the case of the flax, it says
each individual tooth is, if broken off individually, is טמאות, teme'os, because
you could like use it as a toothpick or something. ואף על
גב דלא התקינה. V'af al gav d'lo hiskina. And by the flax
case it doesn't say that you have to do anything to fix
it to make it usable in that fashion. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa,
look at the end by the wool case. אחת והתקינה לנר או
למיתוח טמאה. Achas v'hiskina l'ner o l'mitu'ach teme'ah. One of the teeth
of the wool comb broke off and you did something to fix
it to make it usable, then it's טמאה. teme'ah. התקינה אין לא
התקינה לא, Hiskina in, lo hiskina lo, only if you fixed it.
So you see it's a contradiction. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, ומאי קשיא?
u-mai kushya? Why is that a contradiction? I mean, one's a flax
comb, one's a wool comb. דילמא הא בקנטיסא הא בלימתא. Dilma ha
b'kantisa ha b'limta.
Maybe one is with the, you know, with the, the sort of
the piece on the bottom and one is, you know, you know,
you know how these things are attached to like, you know, on
a comb, right? Does it break off just the tooth or does
it break off with a little bit of the base? Base? Thank
you. Okay,
so oh my god, that's a very interesting comb. Okay, anyway, fine.
But if it breaks off with a little bit of the base,
then you can use it more easily, right? I mean because then
you actually have like a little mini handle attached to it. So
maybe when you don't have to fix it is when it breaks
off with the base, and when you do have to fix it
is when it breaks off without the base. אמר רב פפא, Amar
Rav Papa, ומאי קשיא? u-mai kushya? Here's another way of distinguishing.
דילמא הא בקטינא הא באלימתא. Dilma ha b'katinya ha b'alimta. Maybe one
is a flax, one was wool, maybe one was a thin tooth
and one was a thick tooth. So there's different ways that it
was different that it's not problematic. אלא משום דמסיימי בה דוקא נאי.
Eila mishum d'misaymei bei davka naya.
Okay, you know what, you're right. The משנה mishna is not problematic
at all. But people that are precise about the גרסא, girsa, about
the text, when they finish teaching the whole משנה, mishna, they have
a few words at the end. And what are the few words
they have at the end? זו דברי רבי שמעון. Zu divrei Rabbi
Shimon.
So it's not a סתם משנה. stam mishna. You're right, we don't
rule like that way, but that's because although your version of it
is סתם, stam, there are other versions of it that aren't סתם.
stam. Okay, that was all a huge digression and quite bizarre of
all the cases to ask about not ruling like a סתם משנה
stam mishna that we went over there.
There's five or six different cases that the משנה mishna gave. I
know. Does that mean we don't rule like any of them?
Or I don't know, we don't have to rule like any of
them? I don't know. Okay, now we move back to this issue
of the three months' wait. So we have this big question, right?
We have the question about do we always demand the three months'
wait, or do we say לא פלוג? lo plug? And that was
all issued, do we rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says
we judge it case by case, or do we rule like רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir who says לא פלוג? lo plug? And we said
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan went back and forth on that. So let's
see how the גמרא Gemara ends up. שלח רבי יאשיה בר אבין,
Shlach Rabbi Yoshiyah bar Avin, Rabbi Yoshiyah bar Avin sent, מארסין תוך
ג'. Me'arsin toch gimel.
You could do אירוסין eirusin within three months, okay, which is because
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that אירוסין eirusin is not a problem
because you're not putting yourself, the woman isn't putting herself in a
context where she can be having sex yet. וכן עושין מעשה. V'chen
osin ma'aseh. And that's how we would rule. וכן היה רבי אלעזר
מלמדנו. V'chen haya Rabbi Elazar m'lamdeinu. And this is what רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar would teach us. It's just משום רבי חנינא הגדול *mishum
Rabbi Hanina Hagadol*: רובו של ראשון *rubo shel rishon*, and we'd also
be taught the majority of the first month, ורובו של שלישי *v'rubo
shel shlishi*, and the majority of the third month, ואמצעי והשלם *v'emtza'i
v'hashalem*, and the entire middle month would be enough. Now that's bizarre
and רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafot* don't discuss it. I assume
other ראשונים *Rishonim* did, I did not get a chance to look.
But like, if you really are in a situation where you're demanding
three months, what is this about most of one, the second, and
most of the third? That's not going to do enough of a
job of distinguishing between whose kid it is, unless he feels—he doesn't
buy into what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said before, you don't believe
that a kid could be born after six months and two days,
maybe he felt you needed seven full months. If you felt you
needed seven full months, then two months and a little bit really
would be enough. It's not exactly clear what this other opinion is,
but anyway the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is not focusing on that, it's
focusing on whether you have to wait three—on what situations you have
to wait three months. Yes?
תוספות *Tosafot* says three months, this is only for an ארוסה arusah
*arusah*.
So that was the other possibility, that when he says an ארוסה
arusah *arusah* doesn't have to wait, he didn't mean don't have to
wait at all, he meant you don't have to wait the full
three months, you can use this version of the three months. Then
it's not as lenient of a פסק *psak*. Okay, so that's possible.
It's possible that he's combining those two things. You see the two
separate teachings or a combined teaching. Okay, fine, that's that. Now, אמימר
שרי לארוס ביום תשעים *Amemar sharei l'arus b'yom tishim*. Now that actually
would fit a little bit because now what we're seeing is leniencies
but not much leniencies. Like okay, maybe אירוסין eirusin, *erusin*, not like
we don't demand three months at all, we'll be a little bit
more lenient in how we define the three months. So אמימר *Amemar*
said, you know what, if it's just אירוסין eirusin *erusin* and not
נישואין nisuin, *nisuin*, you can get married on day ninety. You don't
have to wait till day ninety-one. Okay, so alright, thank you. אמר
ליה רב אשי *Amar lei Rav Ashi*, so רב אשי *Rav Ashi*
said to אמימר *Amemar*, הא רבא ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו צריכה להמתין ג'
חדשים *Ha Rava u'Shmuel d'amri tarvaihu tsricha l'hamtin gimmel chodashim*, you have
to wait three months חוץ מיום שמת בו וחוץ מיום שנתארסה בו
*chutz mi'yom shemeis bo chutz mi'yom shenis'arsa bo*, not including the day
of death, you start counting the ninety days after the day of
death, and not including the day that you're doing the אירוסין eirusin
*erusin*, the אירוסין eirusin. *erusin* has to be on day ninety-one. So
first of all they're already talking explicitly אירוסין eirusin *erusin*, even אירוסין
eirusin *erusin* needs three months, right? Even though he's not yet in
a context of having sex. And not even a leniency in counting
the ninety days, it has to be on day ninety-one. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here said, no, ההוא לעניין מינקת איתמר *hahu l'inyan
meneket itmar*. That was said not about the ninety days, that was
said about the waiting before remarrying a woman who is nursing. Remember
we discussed that as well. רבא ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו צריכה להמתין כ"ד
חודש *Rava u'Shmuel d'amri tarvaihu tsricha l'hamtin chaf-daled chodesh*, חוץ מיום שנולד
בו וחוץ מיום שנתארסה בו *chutz mi'yom shenolad bo v'chutz mi'yom shenit'arsa
bo*. The waiting before of a woman who's nursing, it was assumed
nursing would take place for the first two years, so they said
you would have to wait twenty-four months, not including the day that
the baby was born, starting the day after the baby was born,
and that the actual day of the אירוסין eirusin, *erusin* is the
day after the twenty-four months.
So anyway, he said you got the version wrong, it wasn't three
months, it was twenty-four months, it was taught about something else. So
right now we are saying a basic לא פלוג lo plug *lo
pelug*, and at most what we're debating is like can you have
a somewhat creative way of defining the three months in that case?
Maybe that was the first opinion that you just make it like
the majority of three months or maybe that's this idea of at
least counting day ninety and not ninety-one. Okay, so גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says וההוא דעבד סעודת אירוסין seudas erusin. ביום תשעים *v'hahu d'avad seudas
erusin b'yom tishim*. There was a guy, again, all this is אירוסין
eirusin *erusin*. So the end of the סוגיא *sugya*, although in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* we said רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* first said we
go, we don't say לא פלוג lo plug *lo pelug* and אירוסין
eirusin *erusin* you wouldn't need it, here consistently you always are—the end
of the discussion is even by אירוסין eirusin *erusin* you always need
three months. And the most of the discussion is what do you
do about day ninety? So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, wasn't there a
guy that made a סעודת אירוסין eirusin *seudas erusin* on day ninety?
ואפסדיה רבא לסעודתיה *v'afsei de Rava l'seudasei*, and רבא *Rava* basically made
him, you know, made him throw out the whole wedding feast, said
no, I'm sorry, you're not getting married today, you have to wait
till tomorrow to get married. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ההיא סעודת
נישואין nisuin. הוי *hahi seudas nisuin havi*. No, you got the case
wrong. That wasn't a סעודת אירוסין eirusin. *seudas erusin*, that was a
סעודת נישואין nisuin. *seudas nisuin*. נישואין nisuin *nisuin* we would obviously wait
till day ninety-one. So והלכתא כוותיה *v'hilchasa k'vachasei*, צריכה להמתין כ"ד חודש
*tsricha l'hamtin chaf-daled chodesh* when you're waiting twenty-four months, it has to
be a full twenty-four months. So that's by the case of nursing.
חוץ מיום שנולד בו וחוץ מיום שנתארסה בו *chutz mi'yom shenolad bo
v'chutz mi'yom shenis'arsa bo*, and not including the day that the baby
was born and not including the day of the wedding, of the
קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*. וצריכה להמתין ג' חדשים *u'tsricha l'hamtin gimmel chodashim*, and
when you're waiting three months for getting remarried, this woman after her
husband dies or divorces her, חוץ מיום שמת בו *chutz mi'yom shemeis
bo*, not including the day of death, וחוץ מיום שנתארסה בו *u'chutz
mi'yom shenis'arsa bo*, and not including the day of אירוסין Eirusin *erusin*.
So more than the question of day ninety and ninety-one, what's most
significant about the conclusion is that we say the לא פלוג lo
plug, *lo pelug*, that you have to wait three months even in
a case of אירוסין Eirusin *erusin*. Now this again, one might come
to the conclusion that Michael suggested yesterday, which is if we're saying
לא פלוג lo plug. *lo pelug*, then maybe you can't use a
pregnancy test. Maybe לא פלוג *lo pelug*, we say you all need
three months, doesn't matter yes virgin, not virgin, etc. But since the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before did discuss tests, so I say well, why
not have her walk, why not do this, why not do that?
One could say no, לא פלוג *lo pelug* that in all circumstances
we need to determine whether or not she's pregnant, but when... that
determination have to be three months? If we have a definite way
of determining it through some other means, like a modern pregnancy test,
that might be fine even if—so it would be a little bit
funny. You'd say, 'Okay, here's a woman, she's a virgin, she's underage
or whatever, she's post-menopausal let's say.' That's that case. Once post-menopausal, we
say לא פלוג, so therefore take a pregnancy test and then we'll
be okay. Right? But that is—there are two separate questions. One is
do we demand some way of determining? And then is that way
of determining only three months or in theory—theory if we could find
another means, we would be happy with that other means? And it
makes a certain amount of sense, because saying לא פלוג is not
saying like we really believe that this post-menopausal woman might be pregnant.
Saying לא פלוג is we don't want to start distinguishing the cases,
because there'll be some cases that we would really need to determine
it, and then by making distinctions, some of those cases will slip
through the cracks. So we're going to demand it in all cases.
Fine, we'll demand in all cases, but what are we going to
demand? Let's demand a pregnancy test. We don't necessarily demand three months.
It's a מחלוקת הפוסקים machloket haposkim whether you can use pregnancy tests
here.
And you're saying that if you would, would you make old women
take them?
Yeah. According to that logic, you would. You would
do—even an older woman, you would have to do a pregnancy test
and then you'd be done. Yeah.
What's the case? In the case of יבום, yibum, someone has a—had
a kid, right? Yeah. And then, how long is אבילות aveilut for
a kid? Is it a month or is it a year?
I'm sorry, what?
Is it a month or is it a year?
Is what a month or year?
אבילות aveilut for a kid? Because she loses a child.
No, it's a month. It's only אבילות aveilut for—is for more than
a year for a parent.
And how come it's חוץ מן האלמנה, chutz min ha'almanah, let's say
she loses a kid, but she also has to wait a month
for—well, no, no, no.
That's—first of all, אבילות aveilut from her husband—we're going to get to
the—she's an אלמנה almanah and
she had a kid, but she lost the kid.
Are you making a case about the miscarriage? No,
what kid are you talking about? It's just the case that her
husband died.
The only exception
is
potentially is אלמנה almanah מפני האיבול. mipnei ha'ibul.
Right, so—all right, there could be other cases that people are thinking
of. Maybe she's in שבעה shiva for her parent or whatever. But
that's not intrinsic to the case. Okay, so that's exactly what we
turn to now, is the position of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, that
if this—although he says—although if she's only doing אירוסין, Eirusin, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi says you can get married right away. Again, but now
this new set—this new reality of אירוסין Eirusin doesn't—is not yet in
the context of sex. So אירוסין Eirusin he said you could do
right away. He says that's not in a case when a woman
just lost her husband, her husband died, then you cannot do it
within the first month because then she is still in אבילות. aveilut.
The problem that the גמרא Gemara, is going to have is that
we normally assume that there's no אבילות aveilut for husband and wife
until after the נישואין, nisuin. not at the stage of אירוסין. Eirusin
So what is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi talking about in terms of
אבילות? aveilut? Okay, that now you could say, okay, maybe that's—that's when
she was נשואה nesuah before. All right, so she's נשואה, nesuah, right?
Meaning there's two stages, right? The point here is
remarrying. I'll just use the board for a second. But anyway, like
here she is, right? Here's רחל Rachel married to ראובן. Reuven. Okay,
he died. They were נשואים. nesuim. So she has to sit שבעה
shiva for him. She's in אבילות aveilut for a month. Okay. And
now, but she's only going to do אירוסין Eirusin. with שמעון. Shimon.
So since she's only doing אירוסין Eirusin. with שמעון, Shimon, she can
do that right away because there's no—because they're not having—they're not having
kids right away. אירוסין, Eirusin right, you don't have the possibility of
having kids until נישואין. Nisuin. So you can do this right away,
you don't have to wait three months. But in the first month
she's still sitting שבעה, shiva, she's still in אבילות aveilut for ראובן.
Reuven. Now, if she was only ארוסה arusa, to ראובן, Reuven, it
wouldn't be a problem basically because there's no אבילות aveilut for a
relationship that was just an ארוסה arusah, relationship. But she was נשואה
nesuah to ראובן, Reuven, he died, she's in אבילות aveilut for a
month. So even though this אירוסין Eirusin. can happen right away because
they're not yet having sex, but nevertheless, you have to wait at
least a month so that she's no longer in אבילות. aveilut. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara חוץ מן האלמנה. Chutz
min ha'almanah. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
He says, I don't get it. I don't get
why this makes sense. I'll tell you a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
ומה במקום שאסור לכבס, מותר לארס. Umah bimkom she'asur lachabes, mutar learess.
He says, I don't think that אירוסין Eirusin itself should be a
problem when a person is during the month of אבילות, aveilut, or
even during the שבעה. shiva. Right, because remember the שמחה simcha comes—primary
שמחה simcha comes through נישואין. Nisuin, And you might know the הלכה
halacha by the way that you can actually do קידושין Kiddushin? as
opposed to נישואין Nisuin even on like תשעה באב Tisha B'Av itself,
because the גמרא—שמואל says שמא יקדמנו אחר. shema yekadmenu acher. Right,
somebody else will beat you to it. So anyway, so this woman's
being—whatever, she's—so anyway, so now he's saying look, since we're talking only
about אירוסין Eirusin here because otherwise it would be a problem of
waiting three months, why is this a problem during the—during אבילות? aveilut?
Since when is אירוסין Eirusin. a problem during אבילות? aveilut? It's not
talking about נישואין. Nisuin, So קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה במקום שאסור
לכבס מותר לארס. Umah bimkom she'asur lachabes mutar learess. A
place where you're not allowed to do laundry because of אבילות aveilut
issues, you're still allowed to do אירוסין. eirusin, מקום שמותר לכבס, Makom
shemutar lachabes,
during the month, right, you're only not allowed to do laundry during
the— during the first week, during the rest of the month where
you're allowed to do laundry in אבילות, Aveilus, אירוסין שמותר לארס Eirusin
shemuttar l'arais how much more so should אירוסין eirusin? be allowed? מאי
היא, Mai hee, now what is this case where you can do...
you can not do laundry but you can do קידושין? Kiddushin, תנן,
Tnan, we taught. שבת שחל תשעה באב להיות בתוכה, Shabbos shechol Tisha
B'Av lihyos besochah, the week of תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, שבוע שחל
בו תשעה באב. Shavua shechol bo Tisha B'Av. אסור לספר ולכבס, Assur
l'saper u'lchabbes, you can't get a haircut and do laundry. ובחמישי מותר
מפני כבוד שבת, U'vachamishi muttar mipnei kevod Shabbos, on Thursday you can
for שבת Shabbos purposes, so that's bracketed. ותניא, V'tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא. Braisa. קודם הזמן הזה, Kodem hazman hazeh, before this before
this time, presumably meaning before תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, העם ממעטין בעסקיהם
מלבנות ומליטע, Ha'am mematin b'iskeihem milivnos u'milita,
you don't do business and building and so on, ומארסין, u'maarsin, but
you can still do קידושין, Kiddushin. אבל לא כונסין, aval lo konsin,
but you can't bring the woman in, can't do נישואין. Nisuin ואין
עושין סעודת אירוסין, V'ein ossin seudas Eirusin, but you can't do an
אירוסין eirusin, like feast, but you can still do the act of
קידושין. Kiddushin. So you see, אף אירוס, af eirus, yeah, that's קידושין.
Kiddushin So you see that's presumably that's שבוע שחל בו, Shavua shechol
bo, you can do קידושין Kiddushin. even though you can't do laundry.
How much more so during the rest of the month where you're
allowed to do laundry, you should be able to do קידושין. Kiddushin,
So גמרא Gemara says no. כי תניא היא קודם דקודם. Ki tanya
hee kodem d'kodem. No no no, when that says before this time,
it doesn't mean שבוע שחל בו, Shavua shechol bo, it means before
the שבוע שחל בו Shavua shechol bo you're allowed to do קידושין,
Kiddushin. but during the שבוע שחל בו Shavua shechol bo you're not
allowed to do קידושין. Kiddushin. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, וקודם דקודם נמי
קל וחומר. u'kodem d'kodem nami kal v'chomer. So what? I'll make a
קל וחומר kal v'chomer during before the שבוע שחל בו. Shavua shechol
bo. ומה במקום שאסור לישא וליתן, U'mah bimkom she'assur lisa v'liten, remember
you're not allowed to do business right, משנכנס אב ממעטין בשמחה. mishenichnas
Av mematin b'simcha.
So the whole the whole nine days you're not allowed to do
business, ומותר לארס, u'muttar l'arais, but you can still do קידושין. Kiddushin
מקום שמותר לישא וליתן, Makom shemuttar lisa v'liten, when you're allowed to
do business like during the rest of the month of Shiva we're
switching back from תשעה באב Tisha B'Av period to personal personal אבילות.
aveilus. When you're allowed to do business during the rest of the
month of אבילות, aveilus, not during the first week, אינו דין שמותר
לארס, eino din shemuttar l'arais, how much more so should קידושין Kiddushin
be allowed during the first month of אבילות. aveilus. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא תימא דרבי יוסי אומר כל הנשים יתארסו, lo teima
d'Rabbi Yossi omer kol hanashim yisarsu, fine.
So the first answer is, I'm just going to tell you the
answer at the end because it's going to be a little frustrating
in the middle before we get there. The answer at the end
is going to be, you can't compare תשעה באב Tisha B'Av הלכה
Halacha to personal אבילות. aveilus. In תשעה באב Tisha B'Av הלכה Halacha
it's not as personal so therefore you we will allow קידושין Kiddushin.
under certain circumstances. Personal אבילות aveilus is much more highly specific to
the person himself, we're not going to allow קידושין. kiddushin That's going
to be the answer at the end. But at this stage, the
גמרא Gemara in order to make it work, how is it that
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av we allow it and how is it and
how is it here that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi has got a
problem, we're going to completely switch the גירסא girsa of רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi and say that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is saying the
problem here is not אירוסין, eirusin? אירוסין eirusin. is not a problem,
and what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is actually saying the problem here
is נישואין, Nisuin and we're going to go through a whole עמוד
amud now of switching the גירסא girsa of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi.
Yes, very good.
And regarding the business, most people I know work normally during the
nine days except for תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av.
Yeah, so there's a question of what type of לישא וליתן lisa
v'liten we're talking about, you know whether it's לישא וליתן של שמחה
lisa v'liten shel simcha etc., we'll worry about it when we do
תענית. Taanis.
Yeah, but you know, although
if
this issue is not for any other reason, then there would still
be a similar concern.
Yeah, but it's just that this is intrinsic to the case. לא
תימא דרבי יוסי אומר כל הנשים יתארסו, Lo teima d'Rabbi Yossi omer
kol hanashim yisarsu, fine. I can see the point. אירוסין eirusin, should
be allowed during the month of אבילות. aveilus. So רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi is not having a problem with saying
with talking about whether women can do אירוסין eirusin or not and
say the season of אבילה aveilah she can't do אירוסין. eirusin. אלא
אימא כל הנשים ינשאו. Ela eima kol hanashim yinassu. What he's saying
is all women can do נישואין Nisuin except for a woman who's
an אלמנה almanah because that's during the month of אבילות. aveilus. So
you're right, he's talking about נישואין, nissuin, he's not talking about אירוסין.
eirusin אירוסין eirusin? would be okay. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute. So נישואין nissuin, is only a problem for the אלמנה? almanah?
Isn't נישואין nissuin a problem for all the women? Right? We're talking
about נישואין nissuin. now, we've switched the terms of the game. וליחש
ליה דרבי יוסי להבחנה? U'leyachush lei d'Rabbi Yossi l'havchanah? Isn't רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi concerned about distinguishing whose child it is? The גמרא Gemara
says לית ליה. lais lei. Yes, he's not concerned. Okay, which is
a great answer from the גמרא, Gemara but oh my god, he's
allowed yeah, he's not concerned about that. I don't know exactly why
not. אי בעית אימא לעולם אית ליה, Ee ba'is eima l'olam ais
lei, fine, he is concerned about whose child it is. ואימא רבי
יוסי אומר כל ארוסות גרושות ינשאו. V'eima Rabbi Yossi omer kol arusos
grushos yinassu. What he's saying is like this, he's saying not he's
saying all women who are ארוסות arusos can go ahead and well
let me just check the רש"י for a second.
ארוסות Arusos yeah, hold on. I thought you didn't need it for
אירוסין. eirusin
Right, right, right. Meaning, meaning, he's reversing the order. Right? He is
saying, right, remember if if you don't say לא פלוג, then if
one of these stages of אירוסין eirusin you don't have to worry
because there's no sex. Like it's only a problem if there's sex
at both ends. So instead of saying all נשואות nesuos can do
אירוסין eirusin? except for during the case of an אלמנה almanah because
then she's in אבילות, aveilus, now we're saying there's no you that
wouldn't prevent אירוסין. eirusin So we're going to switch the terms. Not
anything, we're going to say here she's an ארוסה, arusah, so that's
why it's not a לא פלוג. That's why there's no concern of
whose child it is, and here she's undergoing נישואין, nissuin right? So
we switched them. As opposed to this being a נשואה nesuah and
this being ארוסה, arusah, and that's because this is an ארוסה, arusah
there's no concern of whose child it is. But oh, if it's
only אירוסין, eirusin. there's no אבילות aveilus concern. Okay, flip it. This
is the ארוסה, arusah so there's no concern of whose child it
is. This is the נישואין, nissuin and now women are normally allowed
to do נישואין nissuin. if they started as an ארוסה arusah because
there's no concern of whose child it is, but they're not allowed
to do it if they're in the first month of אבילות. aveilus.
That's why it says כל הגרושות, kol hagerushot, if she's a divorcee,
if she's an ארוסה arusah who's a divorcee, מן האירוסין, min ha'eirusin,
then she can do נישואין. nissuin. But if she's an ארוסה arusah
who's an אלמנה, almanah, then she's in אבילות, aveilus, and then she
cannot. מה היא?
אלמנה מן האירוסין? Mah hi? Almanah min ha'eirusin? An אלמנה almanah from
אירוסין?
eirusin. Can she... Yeah, yeah. Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to ask about. Okay, but okay, so then let's take because
now, right, that's gonna now pose that question, right? So okay, אי
הכי היינו רבי יהודה. ei hachi hainu Rabbi Yehuda.
So that's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
so again, is that exactly clear why it asks that's רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Yehuda? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda just says anyway you can do
either as long as either end is
אירוסין, eirusin, you don't have to wait. הגמרא Gemara says no, איכא
בינייהו נשואה לאירוס. ika beina'ihu nesuah le'eirus. No, the difference is is
when a woman starts off as a נשואה, nesuah, can she do
אירוסין? eirusin רבי יהודה סבר נשואה מותרת לאירוס,
Rabbi Yehuda savar nesuah
muteres le'eirus, רבי יוסי סבר נשואה אסורה לאירוס. Rabbi Yossi savar nesuah
asurah le'eirus.
So basically, he's only allowing
an ארוסה arusah to do נישואין nissuin, and then talking about whether
or not there's a marriage concern, whereas what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
does is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows either, either an ארוסה arusah
can do נישואין nissuin or a נשואה nesuah could do אירוסין. eirusin.
Okay, so רבי יהודה סבר נשואה Rabbi Yehuda savar nesuah can do
אירוסין, eirusin, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is only talking about, it
would maybe assume that a נשואה nesuah could not do אירוסין eirusin,
and he's only talking about an ארוסה arusah doing נישואין. nissuin Okay,
have I completely confused you? But the basic point is רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda doesn't care as long as one of those stages is
אירוסין. eirusin, What we are saying now is that רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi is focusing in on this scenario: that the first stage is
אירוסין erusin and the second stage is נישואין. nissuin. That he says
is allowed except that in the case of אלמנה almanah she has
to wait for the month. So now the גמרא Gemara says, וסבר
רבי יוסי נשואה אסורה לאירוס? Vesavar Rabbi Yossi nesuah asurah le'eirus? Does
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi say that a נשואה nesuah cannot do אירוסין?
erusin Meaning, again, it's not exactly clear what moves the גמרא Gemara
to say this, because the גמרא Gemara until this point, the whole
debate between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi had
really just been whether there's a concern about אבילות aveilus or not,
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi introduces the idea of אבילות. aveilus. For
some reason, now that the גמרא Gemara is switching the parameters, and
I can't really explain to you why, it's assuming that if רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi is talking about this case about an ארוסה doing
נישואין, nissuin, that that would mean that in order to make him
different from רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he would reject the case of
a נשואה nesuah doing אירוסין erusin, and saying a נשואה nesuah doing
אירוסין erusin. would not be allowed under any circumstance. Okay, not exactly
clear why the גמרא Gemara, is assuming that, but that's what it
is. And now it's questioning that assumption. וסבר רבי יוסי נשואה אסורה
לאירוס? Vesavar Rabbi Yossi nesuah asurah le'eirus? Would רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
say a נשואה nesuah can't do אירוסין? erusin והתניא רבי יוסי אומר
כל הנשים יתארסו חוץ מאלמנה מפני האיבול. Vehatanya Rabbi Yossi omer kol
hanashim yeit'arsu chutz me'almanah mipnei ha'eibul.
All women can do אירוסין erusin? except for אלמנה almanah because of
the אבילות. aveilus. So anyway, by the way, that's back to what
the משנה Mishna is saying, right? All women except for an אלמנה
almanah doing אירוסין. erusin, We're back to the woman who was a
נשואה nesuah now doing אירוסין. וכמה איבול שלושים יום, Vechama eibul shloshim
yom,
and for thirty days. וכולן לא ינשאו. Vechulan lo yinase'u.
And that's about an אלמנה almanah doing אירוסין, but all women, presumably
all ארוסות arusot shall
not, excuse me, all women even נשואות nesu'ot cannot do נישואין nissuin.
עד שיהו להם ג' חדשים. ad she'yehu lahem gimel chadashim. Okay,
so again, the simple sense of this ברייתא beraita is what the
משנה Mishna said, that אירוסין is okay except for אבילות aveilus purposes,
but נישואין nisuin, is no good. So the גמרא says, היי מאי
קושיא? Hai mai kushya? Why is that? אילימא דקתני רבי יוסי אומר
כל הנשים יתארסו. Eileima deka'tani Rabbi Yossi omer kol hanashim yeit'arsu. All
women can have אירוסין. And that you assume that that means that
all נשואות nesu'ot can have אירוסין, and which is exactly what he
said in the משנה. Mishna. So מי אלים ממתניתין? Mi alim mimatnitin?
So how's that stronger than our משנה? Mishna? The same way we
completely changed the version of our משנה, Mishna, we'll change the version
of the ברייתא. beraita. Okay, דאוקימנא בארוסות. De'okimna be'arusot. So by the
משנה Mishna we said we're not talking about נשואה nesuah doing אירוסין,
we said we were talking about the opposite, ארוסות גרושות arusot gerushot
doing נישואין ינשאו. nissuin yeinasu. Okay, הכא נמי כל ארוסות גרושות ינשאו.
Hacha nami kol arusot gerushot yinase'u. So we completely reverse the text
of the ברייתא. beraita. Okay, both the משנה Mishna and the ברייתא
beraita has רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying a נשואה nesuah can do
אירוסין, and we reverse it to say an ארוסה can do נישואין.
nisuin Okay, אלא מסיפא דקתני וכולן לא ינשאו עד שיהיו להם ג'
חדשים. Ella misseifa deka'tani vechulan lo yinase'u ad she'yehu lahem gimel chadashim.
But when it comes to נישואין, nisuin, you have to wait three
months. Okay,
so this is about a נשואה, nesuah, and a נשואה nesuah cannot
do נישואין. nisuin. הא אירוסי שפיר דמי. Ha eirusai shapir dami. Fine,
we might as well re-read the end of the ברייתא braisa, *Braisa*
also. רבי יוסי אומר *Rebbi Yossi omer* כל הארוסות הגרושות יינשאו *kol
ha'arusos ha'gerushos yinase'u* and an ארוסה *arusa* who's a גרושה grushah *gerusha*
not in אבלה *aveila* can do נשואין *nisuin*, חוץ מן האלמנה *chutz
min ha'almana* מפני האיבול *mipnei ha'eibul* except for אלמנה almanah. *almana* because
of the אבלה *aveila*, וכמה איבול שלה שלושים יום *ve'chama eibul shela
shloshim yom* and that's for thirty days. So that's about a woman
who's an ארוסה *arusa*. An ארוסה *arusa* can do נשואין *nisuin* unless
she's an אלמנה *almana*. Now in the reverse case, בנשואות *be'nisu'os* if
she started off as a נשואה *nisua*, לא יתארסו *lo yis'arsu* עד
שיהיה להם שלושה חודשים *ad she'yiheye lahem shlosha chodashim* have to wait
three months. ואלמנה מן האירוסין *ve'almana min ha'eirusin*... okay fine. So anyway,
that was very, very complicated and just completely rewriting all the text.
And what's really not even unclear is why the גמרא *Gemara* assumes
that just because we flipped this case for רבי יוסי *Rebbi Yossi*,
why he would have to hold that a נשואה *nisua* is always
a problem. Why can't he hold like רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* holds?
As long as one of the ends is אירוסין *eirusin* you're okay.
All right, whatever. The basic thing that you got to know is
that the גמרא *Gemara* says is bothered with why should אירוסין *eirusin*
be a problem during אבלה *aveila*? And what it has answered is
that we're going to flip the case and say it starts as
ארוסה *arusa*, that's why there's no need of three months, and it's
נשואין *nisuin* that's problematic for אבלה *aveila*. But now the גמרא *Gemara*'s
going to ask, so forget all that whole rewrite, that's not so
relevant. What the גמרא *Gemara*'s going to ask though is if you
flip the case, why is there אבלה *aveila* for a husband who
died who you were just an ארוסה *arusa* to? Okay, so either
way it's a question. If the ארוסה *arusa* is at the new
end, that should not create be a problem to get married during
אבלה *aveila*, to do קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* as opposed to נשואין *nisuin*.
And if the ארוסה *arusa* is at this end, well why is
there אבלה *aveila* in the first place? Okay, so now the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this: ואלמנה מן האירוסין מי אית לה איבול *ve'almana
min ha'eirusin mi is lah eibul*? Does a somebody who's a widow
from אירוסין *eirusin* have אבלה *aveila*? והתני רבי חייא בר אמי *ve'hatani
Rebbi Chiya bar Ami* אשתו ארוסה *ishto arusa* that a man's wife
who is just his ארוסה *arusa* to him, not yet נשואה *nisua*,
so they don't yet have a lived relationship, it's just contractual at
this point, לא אונן *lo onen* he is not an אונן *onen*
for her if she dies, ולא מיטמא לה *ve'lo mitame lah* if
he's a כהן kohen. *kohen* he does not become טמא *tamei* to
her, וכן היא לא אוננת ולא מיטמאה לו *ve'chen hi lo onenes
ve'lo mitama'ah lo* if he dies, she's not an אוננת *onenes* and
she doesn't become טמא *tamei* to him, which obviously there's not a
הלכה halacha *halacha* about her as for like a prohibition of כהונה
*kehunah*, but it means she does not have to busy herself with
his burial obligation. מתה אינו יורשה *mesa eino yorsha* when she dies,
he does not inherit her. מת הוא *mes hu* if he dies,
גובה כתובתה *govah kesuvashah* she would never anyway inherit her husband even
if they were נשואות *nisu'os*, but so what she does is but
here interestingly she is at least entitled to a כתובה kesubah *kesuvah*
even though it's only אירוסין *eirusin*. This is in a place where
the כתובה kesubah *kesuvah* obligation, not the ongoing כתובה kesubah, *kesuvah* obligations,
but the basic 200 זוז zuz *zuz* would be promised from the
time would be indebted from the time of the אירוסין *eirusin*. אלא
*ela* anyway you see that there's no אבלה *aveila*. Okay, so we
basically are back to where we started. Nobody debates that there's no
אבלה *aveila* in this—everybody agrees that there's no אבלה *aveila* if it
was just an
ארוסה *arusa* relationship. You would not have to wait. This has to
be a נשואה *nisua*. And if it's a נשואה *nisua*, then this
in order so that it's not no need for a three-months wait,
goes back to אירוסין *eirusin*. If this is back to אירוסין *eirusin*,
why is אירוסין *eirusin* a problem during the אבלה *aveila* period? And
now we finally get back to the original question with all skipping
over their whole complicated rewrite in the middle. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says אלא תנאי היא *ela tana'ei hi*, this issue of אירוסין *eirusin*
during אבלה *aveila* is a debate of תנאים *tana'im*. You showed that
it wasn't a problem during the תשעה באב Tisha B'Av. *Tisha B'Av*
period, it's really a debate of תנאים *tana'im*. דתניא *detanya* we taught
in a ברייתא braisa
*Braisa* מראש חודש ועד
התענית *merosh chodesh ve'ad hata'anis* from ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* until the
fast, the nine days, ממעטין בעסקיהם מלישא ומליתן *mema'atin be'iskeihem milisa umiliten*
you limit the amount of business you do, מלבנות ומלנטוע ומליארס ומלישא
*milivnos umilinto'a umile'ares umilisa* from doing building and planting and from אירוסין
*eirusin* and נשואין *nisuin*. So this says even during the nine days
you don't do אירוסין *eirusin*. שבת שחל תשעה באב Tisha B'Av להיות
בתוכה *shabbos she'chal Tisha B'Av lihyos besochah* and the שבוע שחל בו
*shavu'a she'chal bo* תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av* אסור לספר ולכבס
*assur lesaper u'lechabes* you can't even get a haircut and do your
laundry. ויש אומרים כל החודש אסור *ve'yesh omrim kol hachodesh assur* and
some say that even the whole nine days you don't get a
haircut and do laundry. Okay, so there's an opinion that says אירוסין
*eirusin* is a problem during אבלה *aveila* and that's who רבי יוסי
*Rebbi Yossi* is going like. That explains by the way why he's
arguing with רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*, because maybe only רבי יוסי *Rebbi
Yossi* says it's a problem to אירוסין *eirusin* during the אבלה *aveila*.
So מתקיף לה רב אשי *matkif lah Rav Ashi* רב אשי *Rav
Ashi* asked, ממאי דליארס ליארס ממש *mimmay dele'ares le'ares mamash* how do
you know in that ברייתא braisa *Braisa* by תשעה באב Tisha B'Av
*Tisha B'Av* it was talking about literally just the act of קידושין
kiddushin, *kiddushin*? דילמא למיעבד סעודת אירוסין הוא דאסור *dilma lema'avad se'udas eirusin
hu de'assur* maybe it means only doing like a wedding feast for
the act of אירוסין *eirusin*. But the act of אירוסין *eirusin* maybe
it's okay and we're back to square one. הא ליארס שפיר דמי
*ha le'ares shapir dami* so maybe it's okay to do just the
act of קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*. Back to square one. אי הכי *ei
hachi* מלישא נמי *milisa nami* if that's true then you would say
when it says you can't do נשואין *nisuin*, למיעבד סעודה seuda נמי
*lema'avad se'uda nami*... למהוי סעודת נישואין הוא דאסור, הא לישא שפיר דמי?
ha lisha shapir dami? Would you say the same thing that when
it says here you can't do נישואין, it only means you can't
do a wedding feast or the act of wedding you can do?
So the גמרא says and we know that's not true, so the
גמרא says הכי השתא, hachi hashta, that's not a comparison. בשלמא נישואין
דלא סעודה איכא שמחה. bishlama nisuin d'la seuda ika simcha.
I understand נישואין without the without the feast is still a שמחה.
simcha. They start living together, it's a real marriage. אלא אירוסין בלא
סעודה מי איכא שמחה? ela erusin belo seuda mi ika simcha? But
אירוסין by itself there is no שמחה, simcha, so meaning I'm committed
to the idea that אירוסין is not a problem during during אבילות
avelus and therefore I'm going to even if you have a ברייתא,
if first of all all the evidence shows that it's not a
problem אירוסין, even if you show me a ברייתא that says it
is a problem, I'm going to choose to interpret it as סעודת
אירוסין. So we're back to square one. What's Rabbi Yossi's problem? Because
I think you can do קידושין kiddushin. during the nine days as
as we know the הלכה halacha. is you can even do קידושין
during תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av So what's Rabbi Yossi's problem? So the
גמרא says well then the אלא אמר רב אשי, ela amar rav
ashi, שאני אבילות חדשה מאבילות ישנה. shani avelus chadasha me'avelus yeshana. No,
there's a difference between a new אבילות avelus and an old one.
Old one תשעה באב which is like a commemorative אבילות avelus that
we're supposed to get into that experience but it's not really fresh,
so the the demands are not as weighty as opposed to the
demands of a of a fresh אבילות. avelus. And ושאני אבילות דרבים
מאבילות דיחיד. veshani avelus derabbim me'avelus deyachid. Now this could go both
ways. You could say a communal אבילות avelus is more weighty, right,
it's something that affects the entire people. But also it's less personal
as opposed to a personal אבילות, avelus, that's more personal. So you
know what you might be right. Might be even on תשעה באב
you could do קידושין, but at least what Rabbi Yossi is saying
maybe Rabbi Yehuda disagrees, but whatever evidence you bring from תשעה באב
is not relevant. And Rabbi Yossi is at least entitled to say
that in a personal new אבילות avelus there should be an איסור
issur of קידושין, so we're back to the simple read of the
משנה. Mishnah. Yes, it's just אירוסין. Maybe it's not a problem during
the תשעה באב period, but Rabbi Yossi is saying it is a
problem during this personal אבילות avelus period. Yes Dov, you had a
question.
Can I corroborate something that I always thought. I don't know if
it's הלכה. halacha But if someone is in אבילות, avelus, they say
I'll go to the wedding just for the חופה chuppah but not
for the סעודה with the music. Yeah. But the חופה chuppah itself
is such a מעשה. maiseh. Right. Always seemed to me you shouldn't
go at all if you're going to be מקפיד. makpid.
Yeah so that's true. I mean so there are different issues. Are
we talking about during י"ב חודש לאביו ולאימו yud beis chodesh l'av
u'l'emo and are we talking about other cases where you're a relative
and that not going would be a real, you know, a real
issue for the חתן כלה. chosson kallah. I mean whatever, there's a
lot of distinctions, you know. But yes.
I wanted to ask a question also vis a vis I know
that we don't our מנהג minhag is not like the הלכה regarding
אירוסין but do any, you know, פוסקים poskim deal with the issue
of propriety of getting engaged if like let's say your, you know,
fiancee dies or something like that during that time or does no
one care?
No, there are issues about that. The גמרא talks about it about,
you know, even בית הקברות, beis hakvaros, somebody basically approached, you know,
you know, there's a case in the גמרא about that,
a man whose wife had just died approached, you know, approached I
think his sister, the wife's sister or the wife's whatever. Anyway, but
the basic point was was that that was done, you know, also
because of a feeling like needed to marry somebody because he had
to provide for the household. Yeah so there is a discussion there
around the propriety issues. Chananya did you have a question? Now also
with our with our, I don't I don't know. I mean there's
always propriety questions.
We're just talking about הלכות אבילות hilchos avelus here. We're not talking
about the three months, the one month.
Well that's the point, within the context of waiting three months or
whatever you're saying wait wait, you forgot about the fact that if
her husband died, there's an אבילות avelus issue to discuss. That's all
he's saying but that's taking it from some different area, right, yeah.
Is the כתובה given at אירוסין?
Is the כתובה
the ongoing obligations of the כתובה, the ones that are affect sort
of during the reciprocal
relationship obligation during נישואין, not during קידושין. The only question is does
the base amount, the 200 זוז that's like the lump sum payment
in the case of divorce or death etc. to protect her, you
know, because to provide for her, um, that might already be at
the time of אירוסין, that's what this ברייתא assumed. Okay.
But it's not given until then נישואין.
The basically clothing and food and and, you know, domicile etc. Yeah.
Okay so let's just we're actually ahead, not ahead, we're up, caught
up. Let's get to the next דף. daf. We'll be ahead for
once. We'll read the משנה. Mishnah. ארבעה אחים נשואים ארבע נשים
ומתו.
arbaa achim nesuim arba
nashim u'mesu. No no, it's not going to be as complicated as
you think. Okay.
Four four brothers are married to four women, notice it doesn't even
say they're sisters. I know. It basically just wants to give you
a scenario where one brother is confronted with multiple ייבום yibbum opportunities
from multiple brothers. Okay.
ומתו. u'mesu. All these four brothers die. And now there's another fifth
brother around. אם רצה הגדול שבהם לייבם את כולן הרשות בידו. im
ratza hagadol shebahem leyabem es kulan harashus biyado.
So we've already said that the responsibility devolves around the oldest brother.
If now if there are four women there that are four from
four different brothers waiting for ייבום, yibbum, he can choose to do
ייבום yibbum with all of them, right, and they you know, so
it doesn't say no you do one now the other brothers have
their primary responsibility with the other. מי שהיה נשוי לשתי נשים ומת.
mi shehaya nasui lishtei nashim u'mes.
Somebody was married to two women and he died. ועשה חליצה של
אחת מהן פוטרת צרתה. v'asah chalitzah shel achat me-hen potert tzaratah. This
we've known from the beginning, right? The act of sex with one
of them or the act of חליצה chalitzah with one gets all
the others off the hook.
ביאה או חליצה Bi'ah o chalitzah is done with one and the
others automatically are now free. היתה אחת כשרה ואחת פסולה. Haitah achat
k'sherah v'achat psulah.
Let's say of the two wives, one of them was already פסול
לכהונה. pasul l'kehunah. One was already a גרושה grushah from a previous
marriage. Okay, אם היה חולץ, חולץ לפסולה. im hayah choletz, choletz l'psulah.
If you're going to do חליצה, chalitzah, might as well do חליצה
chalitzah with the one who's already a גרושה so you don't make
her פסול pasul to a כהן. Okay, because the other one is
just an אלמנה. ואם היה מיבם, מיבם לכשרה. v'im hayah miyabem, miyabem
l'k'sherah. If you're going to do יבום, yibum,
you should do יבום yibum with the כשרה. k'sherah. Now, that's not
clear. Does it mean you do יבום yibum even with the כשרה
k'sherah only with the כשרה? k'sherah? Fine. We will see in the
גמרא, but we can now say that we are actually a little
bit ahead.